[Music]
foreign
seven years ago I introduced the
endotoxin theory literature which sought
to explain how a single meal of sausage
and Egg McMuffins could artery
function within hours of consumption
maybe because such a meal causes
inflammation by inducing a low-grade
endotoxemia endotoxins in the
bloodstream within hours of consumption
endotoxins are structural components of
gram-negative bacteria like E coli in
certain foods have such high bacterial
loads like ground meat the thought was
that it was the endotoxins in the food
that was triggering the inflammation
critics of the theory argue that because
we have so many bacteria already living
in our colon I mean so many endotoxins
just sitting down there in our large
intestine a few more endotoxins in our
food wouldn't matter much in terms of
causing you know systematic inflammation
after all we have like two pounds of
pure bacteria down there when the sun
don't shine so there could be like a
whole ounce of endotoxin and the lethal
dose of intravenously injected endotoxin
could be just like a few millionths of a
gram so we could have like a a million
lethal doses down there but the apparent
Paradox is explained by
compartmentalization is location
location
poop is harmless in your colon but
shouldn't be injected into your
bloodstream or eaten for that matter
particularly with fatness that can
promote the absorption of endotoxins up
in the small intestine even well cooked
poop you can boil endotoxins for two
hours straight with no detriment in
their ability to induce inflammation and
you could easily kill off any bacteria
if you boiled your poop soup long enough
but you can't kill off the endotoxins
they make just like you can't cook the
crap out of the meat right the
consumption of meat contaminated with
feces doesn't just cause food poisoning
right I mean it can you know spill out
during the evisceration process when the
digestive tract is ruptured even when
slaughterhouse workers trim off the
visible fecal contamination the trimming
itself can ironically sometimes lead to
an increase in certain fecal bacteria
thought to be caused by
cross-contamination from one cargus to
the next then even when properly stored
in the fridge endotoxins start
accumulating along with a bacterial
growth what about other Foods the
highest levels of endotoxins were found
in meat and dairy and the lowest levels
in fresh fruits and vegetables but that
was testing whole fruits and vegetables
most spoilage organisms can't penetrate
the plant's surface barrier and spoil
the inner tissues I mean that's why you
know fruits and veggies can just sit out
there all day in the Sun out in the
fields right but once you cut them open
though and bacteria can gain access to
the inner tissues within a matter of
days your veggies can start to spoil so
what does that mean for all those
convenient pre-chopped veggies these
days while endotoxins were not
detectable in the majority of
unprocessed vegetables once you damage
the protective outer layer of vegetables
you diminish the resistance to microbial
growth so while freshly chopped carrots
and onions start out with undetectable
levels day after day even kept chilled
in the fridge you start to get the
growth of bacteria and along with them
endotoxin buildup not as much as meat
but not insignificant enough to make a
difference though yeah oh no until you
put it to the test what would happen if
you switched people between a diet
expected to have a lower endotoxin load
to foods containing more endotoxins like
going from intact meat like steaks and
whole fruits and vegetables to more like
ground beef and pre-chopped veggies and
more ready-made meals after just one
week on the lower endotoxin diet
people's white blood cell count which is
an indicator of total body inflammation
dropped 12 but then bumped 14 up after
just four days and the higher endotoxin
died and actually lost a pound and a
half on the lower endotoxin diet and
slim their waist a bit
but they weren't really eating otherwise
identical dyes looked like they were
eating more meat and cheese overall on
the higher end of toxin diet and maybe
getting more food additives in the
ready-made meal so how do we know
endotoxins had anything to do with it
that's where the onion study comes in a
new study was designed based on two
meals that differed in their content of
bacterial products but which were
otherwise nutritionally identical so
they compared freshly chopped onion to
pre-chopped onion that had been
refrigerated for a few days I mean it
wasn't spoiled it was still before the
kind of best before date so would it
make any difference
within three hours of consumption the
fresh onion meal caused significant
reductions in several markers of
inflammation that's what fruits and
vegetables do they reduce inflammation
but these effects were not observed
after eating the pre-chopped onions for
example here's one inflammatory marker
three hours after eating fresh chopped
onions a significant drop in
inflammatory status but three hours
after eating the exact same amount of
pre-chopped onions no significant change
so it's not like the pre-chopped onions
caused more inflammation like in the
meat eggs and dairy studies but they did
appear to extinguish some of the
anti-inflammatory effects of the onion
in conclusion the Modern Trend towards
eating the pre-chopped vegetables rather
than whole intact Foods is likely to be
associated with an increased oral
endotoxin exposure I mean it's
definitely still better to eat
pre-chopped vegetables than no
vegetables but chopping your own might
be the healthiest
[Music]
oh